[Music]
so
have things changed from one
administration
to the next regarding our torture
policies and regarding what we are doing
um if you could talk about that like
what you saw as a transition between
maybe different administrations to
where we are now that's a tough
question um and it's because there are
so many
ethical gray areas involved in it it was
during the bush administration of course
that we had a formal
torture program and that we had a formal
system of secret prisons this
archipelago of secret prisons
spread all around the world um that was
supposedly shut down um
after my revelations john mccain at
least said on the floor of the senate
that because i had gone public
the the cia ended the program and shut
down the prisons
between 2005 and finally 2007 when i
went public
uh the the deal that was eventually
worked out
between uh congress and the obama
administration
was then to have even civilian agencies
like the cia
like homeland security follow
the army field manual so if it says in
the army field manual you can't
torture you can't waterboard then you
can't torture and you can't waterboard
the problem is that's an executive
branch document
it's not necessarily a legal document
and so
all anybody would have to do if they
want to
reinstitute a torture program is to just
change the army field manual
that's all you have to do you don't need
congressional approval for that
you don't even need a presidential
finding for that you just do it
so this ban that we have on torture now
is tenuous
with that said we're still seeing
reports not a lot
but enough to be worrisome
that cia officers
homeland security officers military
uh personnel are torturing prisoners
we we get these reports mostly from
afghanistan sometimes from syria
somalia elsewhere uh and they're not
being punished for it
why not where are the congressional
oversight committees
why isn't the intelligence committee
looking into this or the armed services
committee or the homeland security
committee
if we have these laws on the books
banning torture then let's
ban torture by god right american people
guess at it
and let's let's talk about another thing
which is which is
you know also very important to this is
that it doesn't work
so so that's that's the thing that that
that
that amazes me is that it's not even
effective
so if this were an effective method and
it saved lives and it
it's still like but it doesn't even work
no the
the cia has an army of psychiatrists and
psychologists
on staff not just contractors although
there are contractors as well
but there's an army within a group
called the office of medical
services oms at the at the cia and
and like dr mengele these guys and and
women
were going out to secret sites to ensure
that the prisoners didn't crack that the
torture stopped
just at the point where they were going
to crack so that they could rest a
little bit and then be tortured more
later
right well you can't do things like that
the hippocratic oath begins
first do no harm we know that
we know from declassified uh cables and
from the senate torture report
that there were physicians and
psychologists and psychiatrists
who were objecting to the torture and
then some of them electing to return to
headquarters
but nobody went public nobody said
anything
finally what they did say to the senate
uh
intelligence committee was that the
torture just simply didn't work
a victim of torture will tell you
literally
anything that they think you want to
hear just to get you to stop
torturing them you know our own
prisoners
during the vietnam war have talked about
this
that they were being tortured and when
asked to give names for example they
would
they would name the starting lineup for
the green bay packers
or they would make up the names of ships
and make up locations for these ships
in the south china sea just anything to
get their torturers to stop
well that's what happened with us and
that's not even going into the fact that
so many cia officers went over and above
what they were authorized to do by the
justice department
causing permanent damage to prisoners i
mean like brain damage
to the point where these prisoners are
unable to participate in their own
defenses
and let's be clear that a lot of these
people might not have even been guilty
of what they were
charged with doing well that's the dirty
little secret of this whole program is
most of them actually were not guilty of
anything
you see we had this program in
afghanistan in the immediate aftermath
of the 9 11 attacks
that we would pay a bounty for any al
qaeda
person uh who a local villager could
turn over to us
well the thing is is if i don't like you
or maybe if i borrowed money from you
and i don't want to pay it back
i just go to the americans and i say hey
there's a there's an arab over there
you might want to take him and then i
get my 500
and you get sent to guantanamo and it's
three or four years before they figure
out that
you're actually not an al-qaeda figure
you're just some guy
who owed who was owed money by this
other villager who turned you in
yeah i think people don't realize that
and i've been saying this for a year and
specifically about gitmo
and the amount of people that are still
rotting away there
that have never been formally charged
never given translators never given a
defense
and very likely are people that were
just disliked
for whatever reason you know abu
zubaydah i think is probably the best
example of this
he's been incarcerated since march of
so 18 and a half years now we're coming
up on 19 years
he's never been charged with a crime
ever with any crime
and when we were going after him we
thought
not only is this guy the number three in
al qaeda but he is so
incredibly dangerous that just to save
the nation
we have to grab him well as it turned
out that wasn't the case at all joe
hickman and i
joe hickman was a was an army
whistleblower
from guantanamo joe hickman and i wrote
a book about abu zubaydah called the
convenient terrorist
and it turns out that what the truth was
was that there were two first cousins
both named abu zubaydah
and if you put in one file
what both cousins were doing they looked
like a terrorist
superman excuse me
a terrorist superman well
they were both moderately bad guys but
not
19 years in prison bad guys right now
one of them
escaped he was actually in the united
states he was in montana
and um when he realized we were looking
for either
him or his cousin he didn't know we
didn't know he fled to jordan we never
we never heard from him again
but abu zubaydah in pakistan
had opened an al-qaeda safe house called
the house of martyrs
in peshawar and he had opened and
managed both of al qaeda's training
camps in southern afghanistan and
kandahar province
he was a logistics guy if you needed a
fake passport to get home if you needed
money or a ticket
uh he'd be the guy to get you out if you
wanted to come and fight the americans
he would be the guy to send you to the
house of martyrs
and then vet you but
he never joined al qaeda he was never a
member
he never pledged loyalty or fealty to
osama bin laden
and after 19 years in prison and
three of those years of being
mercilessly tortured he still hasn't
been
charged with a crime my position is
whether we like his politics or not
he is entitled to the same
constitutional protections that the rest
of us
are and if you're not going to put him
in front of a jury of his peers
and charge him with a crime then you
need to release him
yeah i've been saying that since 9 11
and we started rounding everybody up and
and
i had heard stories of people stuck in
um incarcerated and they weren't even
given translators
so then you know i can't even imagine
how horrifying that is especially if it
is someone that really has nothing to do
with anything and they just get swept up
in this
so then why if we know that torture
doesn't work
right why why is it being done why are
people
like gina haspel still able
to just sort of be out there and doing
what they're doing
you know because it makes us feel better
uh it makes us
feel like first that we're getting
something done and second
it gives us a sense a sense of of
vengeance
where we've we've avenged those 3 000
deaths we haven't it it uh
it's a burden on us a torture program it
cheapens us
and it uh it makes us less of a
of a people of a nation i believe uh but
then you know
i'll tell you a funny little anecdote i
was friendly with a cia
psychiatrist uh we're still friends and
he told me once that the cia actively
seeks to hire people who have
sociopathic tendencies
not sociopaths sociopaths are impossible
to control
right because they don't have a
conscience they blow right through the
polygraph exam
because they don't feel guilt about
anything
the problem is that because they don't
feel guilt
because they blow through a polygraph
exam
it's almost impossible to prevent them
from making their way through the
process
and so the cia is full of sociopaths
i would venture to say and i'm not a
psychologist but
i'm not a psychologist but i'm not an
idiot either i would venture to say that
there are a good number of psychopaths
at the agency as well and we know from
psychological studies on u.s business
leaders
uh most prominently in the book the
psych the the sociopath next door
that people who are sociopaths
are comfortable climbing to the top
on the backs of the people around them
and so just like
in a fortune 500 corporation
the sociopaths and psychopaths at the
cia
claw their way to the top and so they're
the ones
who come up with the idea of a secret
prison system
and a torture program and waterboarding
and sleep deprivation and cold cells
where people freeze to death
and you know they're the ones that
implement these programs